### Emil Hafeez

emil.hafeez@gmail.com / (240) 494-6705 LinkedIn Hyperlink

Decisions-focused evaluator and mixed methods social scientist with experience, education, and goals in program evaluation, data science, and implementation. Team-oriented and collaborative, efficient and process-driven. Interest and experience in applying descriptive and inferential statistics for codifying theoretical and programmatic insights and driving program iteration. Emphasis on co-ownership and equity.

Demonstrated project management and support, including process development, IRB coordination, data collection training, survey design. Ability in multiple analytics sectors, including marketing, financial, and other data-oriented special projects. Published articles in academic scientific journals and literary essay collections, and has presented as a guest poet. Holds USA, Pakistani, and EU citizenships and is very grateful for his broad international experience.

#### Education

Ladoution		
Master of Science, Biostatistics, Theory and Methods	May 2022	
Columbia Mailman School of Public Health, New York, New York		
Master of Science in Public Health, Health Systems		
Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health (JHSPH), Baltimore, MD	May 2018	
Certificate, Evaluation: International Health Programs, JHSPH, Baltimore, MD	May 2018	
Bachelor of Science in Applied Psychology		
Magna Cum Laude, University Honors Scholar, Dean's List		
New York University, New York, NY	May 2015	
Certificate, Philosophy		
University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK	August 2013	

#### Experience

Data Analyst, Consultant May 2019 — September 2020 **Data Analyst Data Coordinator** June 2018 — May 2019

Pencils of Promise, New York, NY

- Data Science: Builds, implements, and interprets quantitative evaluation models for 3 countries' literacy programming, including multiple linear regression models of 2,000+ survey-structured student tests; conducts visualization and communications to international staff; writes publication drafts; role now includes special projects for all departments including ARIMA-based panel data financial forecasting, Google Analytics optimizations, Google Ads development, SEO research, blockchain research and coordination, and donor-facing programmatic case reports
- Data Science: CRM data administrator responsibilities; creates and maintains input, cleaning, and validation processes for Salesforce for ~130 members across all departments; creates reporting and dashboards for dozens of NY- and internationally-based users, supports 3 in-country L&E managers on data, including visits to Ghana, Guatemala, and Laos; Google Analytics, Google Ads, Google Search Console administration
- Advancing Data Systems: Designs, develops, and maintains sustainable CRM architectures to ensure access to and understanding of radically transparent data; builds on existing data structures to improve efficiencies across teams; develops data tracking capabilities; support four countries' usage of software, devices, and L&E systems

### Research Assistant, Lab of Investigation and Development

Bioinformatics Lab., Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia, Lima, Peru June 2017 — June 2018

- Analysis: Implemented data analytics for eve-tracking and pupillometry autism studies: pre-processed 60-variable datasets for 161 case-control participants; conducted descriptive statistics for diagnostic sensitivity and specificity, efficacy, optimization; developed documentation and presentations for PIs and partnered organizations on methods, results, future directions; conducted structural evaluation of Peruvian mental health system for best-practices in this diagnostic tool creation [Publication Pending]
- Operations: Provided research logistics assistance (including health worker training and support, logistical coordination, sampling design discussion, IRB approval) for a 700-household cluster-randomized prevalence study
- Supported MATLAB developers: Created gold-standard reference data: analyzed competing model's frame-by-frame analysis for fidelity to gold-standard; liased between computer engineers and psychologists

#### Research Assistant, Evidence Working Group

March — October 2017

September 2020 —

Bloomberg American Health Initiative, Johns Hopkins, Baltimore, MD

• Created and presented on a complete catalogue of all JHSPH courses for review by the Evidence Working Group leadership, with each course classified by central competencies plus codes for their relevance to public health evidence generation activities; advised on future curriculum changes towards strengthening evidence standards

## Research Assistant, Virtual Population Obesity Prevention (VPOP)

March — June 2017

VPOP Mexico City, Global Obesity Prevention Center, Johns Hopkins, Baltimore, MD

• Extracted baseline probabilities for 17 individual-level variables from dozens of obesity literature reviews and articles to parameterize a virtual population computer model, so as to identify points of leverage for an obesity intervention

### **Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry**

August 2015 — August 2016

Langone Medical Center, New York

## **Book Researcher, Positive Psychology**

August 2015 — August 2016

- Fielded both authors' information requests for source material for various book chapters, by conducting and compiling literature searches on cognitive and social psychology, and neurophysiology; synthesized findings into concise narratives and literature reviews for the author's use, annotated with advice on articulation, organization, and presentation;
- o Edited 8 chapters' manuscripts for accuracy, grammar, and narrative style

# Recitation Leader, Science of Happiness Course

August 2015 — July 2016

 Planned and lead two weekly hour-long undergraduate psychology recitations of about 30 students each in all course material; developed and implemented extracurricular writing tutoring to four students; conducted Teacher Assistant responsibilities including facilitating discussions and application of course material, explaining and grading assignments

#### **Skills and Qualifications**

- Advanced Stata programming and implementation in data preprocessing, parametric and nonparametric significance testing, correlations, regression modeling, diagnostic metrics including sensitivity and specificity optimization, and basic charts and graphs
- Advanced use of Salesforce, Tangerine, and Apsona (including merge and deduplication relational functions)
- Advanced use with research database searches for literature review
- Intermediate use with reference engines EndNote, RefWorks, & Mendeley to structure and share citations with team members
- Basic use of R, RStudio, R Markdown, and the Tidyverse, Git, GitHub, LaTeX, Overleaf
- Basic use of Atlas.ti for qualitative data analysis, experience with Grounded Theory
- G Suite & MS Office proficiencies, Windows and Mac OS X fluency
- Naloxone HCl administration for emergency response to opioid overdose
- Intermediate verbal Spanish

# Select Publications, Presentations, and Reports

- Hafeez, E. (March 20, 2020). Digital Marketing Functions Overview: Services available from NYC Learning & Evaluation [Google Slides presentation]. Pencils of Promise, External Affairs and L&E Teams.
- Hafeez, E. (October 19, 2019). Blockchain and Applications for Maximizing Impact. Graphite: Impact Council Event. Pencils of Promise at Brainstation, NYC [presentation].
- Multiple program evaluation results-sharing presentations, both internal PowerPoints and external-facing blog posts. An example is available here.
- Noazin, S, Jensen, K., et al. (Manuscript in Review). Autism Detection in Children by Combined Eye Tracking and M-CHAT-R in a Resource-Scarce Setting. *Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders*. (Hafeez, E. as data analyst and writer.)
- Hafeez, E., Donis, P., and Carcelén, A. (March 2018). Visual preference for early detection of autism in Peru. Global Health Day, Center for Global Health poster presentation. Baltimore, MD. Similar: Hafeez, E. & Bitterfeld, L. (August 2017). Autism diagnostic study algorithm selection and initial results. [Poster Presentation]. Lima, Peru.
- Developed, coordinated, and received approval on 2 IRB packets at Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, and PRISMA internal review boards. (2017).

CV: Emil N. Hafeez 2